In this lecture, we'll discuss memory, ECC, and interfacing with IO devices.
Main memory and modern systems are built out of commodity DRAM chips, which are inexpensive
and provide very high capacity and reasonable latency.
There's a wide design space for building these chips and optimizing their design objectives
of achieving minimum cost and latency with maximum bandwidth and capacity.
One of the key challenges for main memory that we'll be discussing is soft error detection
and correction.
As we'll discuss later, it is possible for bits to unexpectedly flip or change state,
and we need to be able to protect against these using error correcting codes, or ECC.
ECC is not just used for DRAM.
They're also commonly used in SRAM, data buses, and on-chip and off-chip interconnection
networks.
Here we're showing the typical organization of DRAM main memory.
Recall that each bit is stored as charge in a capacitor.
Thus whenever we read a bit, we actually discharge the capacitor.
This is known as a destructive read, because after we read a bit, we need to write it back
in each time.
Because bits are stored in capacitors, charge also leaks over time, so we need to refresh
our data periodically.
Refreshing simply involves reading out the bits and writing them back in.
Retrieving data from main memory is a long process.
DRAM is optimized for density, not speed.
Given a memory address, we break up its bits into row address and column address, reminiscent
to a page number and page offset respectively.
The first step of a DRAM access is known as a row address strobe, where we pass in the
row address and then read the entire row into the DRAM row buffer, which is known as a page
open command.
The second step is the column address strobe, where we pass in the column address and read
out the specific word from the row buffer.
Then, since each read is destructive, the last step is to write the row back, which
is known as a pre-charge or page closed command.
Let's consider a toy example of accessing a four-word cache block from memory.
Note that we're referring to DRAM bus cycles, not processor cycles.
DRAM bus cycles these days are much slower than CPU cycles.
Each of the commands will be color coded in this example.
First, assume that reading the row to the row buffer takes five DRAM cycles.
Then reading out each word involves one cycle to send the column address on the bus, three
cycles of internal delay in accessing the row buffer in DRAM, and one cycle for receiving
the data word on the bus.
Lastly, we'll assume that pre-charging takes five cycles.
We'll start by assuming a memory bus shown here in this diagram between the L2 cache
and main memory that's only one word wide.
For a simple DRAM implementation, fetching a four-word cache block would be serialized
on the bus.
All of the words of a single block generally reside in the same DRAM row, so the first thing
we do is spend five cycles on the row axis.
Then for each of the four words, we spend one cycle to request its column address, wait
three cycles to request the row buffer, and spend one cycle to send the word to the cache.
Thus the action of fetching the data takes 25 cycles.
Now off the critical path of the processor and cache, we need to pre-charge DRAM in the
background, which takes five cycles.
This means we can't issue the next request until that is completed.
DRAM will typically be able to serve requests in burst mode as in a pipeline banner.
This is because the words being requested are always one after another, so unlike before,
we only need to provide the column address once and specify we want a burst of four words.
Then we'll incur a three-cycle internal delay plus one-cycle read, but this would happen
for all four words in a pipeline.
So then in the end, the effective number of cycles for the request is only 13, followed
by the mandatory five-cycle pre-charge as before.
Often, main memory will be optimized to support wider buses.
Now we have a four-word wide bus between the L2 cache and memory.
Similar to burst mode, we only need to provide the row and column address once, but now,
the DRAM delay and bus read happen in parallel for all four words, leading to only nine cycles
to fetch the entire cache block.
Of course, like cache design, this is only beneficial with spatial locality.
But the rate of improvement in DRAM speeds has been a lot slower than processor speeds,
so programmers are forced to reorganize their memory in order to realize gains provided
by memory width and burst mode.
One of the big challenges with such high-capacity memory is that the probability of a bit flip
or bit failure becomes significant.
Bit flips are considered soft errors in that they do not introduce permanent failures to
the device.
Instead, they are transient and simply need to be reverted back to the correct state.
These bit flips can occur due to gamma rays and alpha particle strikes or electrical interference,
and the likelihood of errors is increasing with smaller feature sizes.
So the standard solution is to employ ECC.
For practical implementations of ECC, we leverage the fact that the probability of bit errors
increases dramatically when we assume more errors.
In other words, given a single memory word, the probability of one bit in it flipping
is much greater than the probability of two bits in it flipping, which is much greater
than more than two bits flipping.
This has limited practical ECC implementations to generally provide protection up to two
errors.
Now, there are two forms of protection, error detection and error correction.
For error detection, we are only concerned with being able to recognize that some number
of bits have flipped, in which case we'll signal a problem to the OS to deal with it
or to kill the program to prevent the generation of incorrect results.
For error correction, we'd like to be able to not just identify the flip bits, but also
revert them back to what they were, all without the software ever knowing.
In an unprotected memory device with no ECC, each bit of data is stored as one bit in memory,
as shown.
We'll refer to the logical data that the program is storing as the data word and the
physical data that is stored in memory as the code word.
Note that even though we call them data words and code words, we're not referring to 32-bit
data in this case.
One important measure for ECC is the hamming distance, which describes the minimum number
of bits that need to be flipped in order to convert one valid code word into a different
valid code word.
With no ECC, the hamming distance is one, since there are only two possible valid code
words, zero and one, and they're just one bit flip from each other.
Single error detection, or SED, is guaranteed with a hamming distance of two.
The most basic implementation is to store one extra bit of redundancy in memory, that
is, every data word is copied once.
In this case, if our data word is one bit, say, zero, then the code word that's actually
stored in memory is two bits, zero, zero.
We can visualize why this yields a hamming distance of two.
Here each node is a possible code word, but only the highlighted ones, zero, zero and
zero, one, are valid.
Each edge represents a possible bit flip that may occur.
Moving from zero, zero to zero, one means bit zero flipped, while moving from zero,
zero to one, zero means bit one flipped.
This scheme provides the ability to detect a single bit flip, since a single bit flip
from either valid code word will always lead us to an invalid code word, zero, one or one,
zero.
In other words, it takes two bit flips to lead to another valid code word, which would
then be undetected.
So if this ever happens, we can signal that an error has occurred and stop the program
from potentially corrupting your files.
But this doesn't provide error correction, because if we observe an invalid code word
in memory, say, zero, one, even though we know a bit flip has occurred, we don't know
what the original valid code word was, because both zero, zero and zero, one are only one
bit flip away.
So to provide single error correction, which provides single error detection for free,
we need a hamming distance of three.
So extending the previous approach, the basic implementation is to use two extra bits of
redundancy instead of one.
Now as shown, the valid code words are only zero, zero, zero and one, one, one.
So now if we observe any invalid code words, assuming that only one bit has flipped, we
can identify exactly which valid code word we had previously, because it would simply
be the closest valid code word.
Now when a single bit flip occurs, we can spot it and correct it on the fly.
The prior approaches can get very expensive for large amounts of data, since they need
a lot of redundant storage.
To improve on that, the standard scheme for single error detection is to use bit parity.
For an arbitrary N bit data word, no matter how big N is, only one parity bit is needed
to detect a single bit flip.
The parity bit is defined as the exclusive OR of all of the bits in the data word.
This is shown in the table below for four bit data words.
The code word is five bits, with the parity being appended on the right.
Now to check if a bit flip has occurred, we compute the syndrome of the code word, which
is simply an exclusive OR of all bits in the code word.
Thanks to the parity bit, the syndrome should always be zero if no error has occurred, because
XOR is zero when there's an even number of ones in a code word.
But if the syndrome is one, then we know that a single bit flip has occurred and can detect
it.
Before we move on, note that the rest of the discussion on ECC uses one based indexing
of bits instead of the typical zero based indexing.
This is to simplify the explanation and be consistent with other literature.
How do we extend this concept of parity to single error correction?
We introduce the concept of hamming codes.
The goal of a hamming code is to add K check bits to an arbitrary N bit data word.
The most common hamming code used in practice is hamming seven comma four, where seven is
the size of each code word and four is the size of each data word.
We'll focus our discussion on hamming seven four codes.
The goal is to encode a four bit data word as a seven bit code word in memory.
Then what we want is to be able to compute a syndrome that points to exactly which bit
in the code word has flipped, if any.
So with the seven bit code word, we need a three bit syndrome, where a syndrome of
zero shown in binary here implies that no bit has flipped.
A syndrome of one implies that bit one has flipped and so on.
Recall that we're using one based indexing here.
So the least significant bit is bit one.
Now let's work backwards to construct a syndrome that can do this.
There are many different ways to implement this.
I'll demonstrate only one method that we'll assume in this course.
The simplest way to construct the syndrome is to set bit one of the syndrome to the
exclusive or of all the odd bits in the code word, w one, w three, w five, and w seven.
This is because the numbers one, three, five, and seven all have their least significant
bit set to one.
Following a similar pattern, bit two of the syndrome is the exclusive or of code words
w two, three, w six, and w seven, since the numbers two, three, six, and seven all have
bit two set to a one.
And finally, bit three is set as the exclusive or of code word bits w four through w seven.
Why did we do this?
Remember the goal of the syndrome is to be equal to zero if no bit flips have occurred.
So let's read our code worded memory and compute the syndrome.
Say it's one zero one.
Syndrome bit one is a one, which means that one of w one, w three, w five, or w seven
has flipped.
Bit syndrome bit three is also a one, which means one of w four, w five, w six, or w seven
w five is the only common word bit in the formulas for S one and S three.
So we know that w five is the flipped bit.
So in this approach, every code word bit affects a unique subset of the syndrome bits.
And that's how we're able to identify and correct the faulty bit.
So then now how do we encode the code word bits?
Well the main thing we want is for each of the syndrome bits to be zero if no bit flip
has occurred.
The simplest option is to take the first bits of each syndrome w one, two and four and use
them as parody check bits.
These three work well because they don't affect any of the other two syndrome bits.
So then w one can be encoded as the exclusive order of the other three code word bits w
three, w five and w seven.
Same goes for w two and w four.
Now the remaining four bits in the code word can be the data itself be one, be two, be
three and be four.
Finally the table on the right shows how to encode each four bit data word into a seven
bit code word in memory.
Then anytime we read the code word we recompute the syndrome and see if any bit has flipped.
Finally as mentioned earlier it's beneficial to provide protection for two bit flips as
well.
But since it's far less common than single bit flips detecting double bit flips is likely
to be sufficient in practice.
We don't need to correct them except in extreme circumstances.
This leads us to single error correction double error detection known as sec dead.
This basically extends the hamming seven four code with an additional parody bit.
This now gives us the hamming distance of four and leads us to a four bit syndrome.
As shown in the table depending on the syndrome bits we're able to identify exactly which
bit has flipped if a single bit flip has occurred.
But if a double bit flip has occurred we can detect this case but we won't be able to
identify which bits exactly have flipped.
To implement this we simply extend the hamming seven four code to have one more syndrome
bit and one more code word bit.
Like in single error detection this additional parody syndrome bit SP is just the exclusive
or of the entire code word.
And the additional bit W8 of the code word is the exclusive or of the other seven bits.
So now if SP is computed to be one then we know that one bit flip has occurred and we
can find out which one based on the typical hamming seven four approach.
But if SP is computed to be zero but at least one of the other syndrome bits is one then
we know that two bit flips has occurred.
Let's look at a quick example of how to encode a sec dead code word.
So given a data word zero one zero one we simply follow the equations on the right most
table and this gives us the code word zero zero one zero one one zero one.
To highlight the strength of the sec dead encoding let's compare it to applying one
bit redundancy.
Both methods convert a four bit data word into an eight bit code word but with the hamming
and parody encoding we're able to provide stronger protection of single error correction
and double error detection whereas one bit redundancy only provides single error detection.
We've discussed input output devices before in the form of disks.
Naturally in order for people to interface with our computer programs they need mechanisms
for providing input signals and mechanisms for receiving output signals.
These I O devices include video displays keyboards your mouse audio etc.
I O is also necessary for large scale storage of persistent or non volatile media and files.
I O is also needed to allow independent computers to communicate with each other via networking.
To give us some context let's first talk about a very important I O device magnetic
disks for storage.
These have been around for many decades now and have continued to improve in terms of
capacity and cost.
Very briefly magnetic disks are physical stacks of platters.
Both the top and bottom of each platter are used as surfaces and each surface consists
of multiple tracks.
The track head is able to move to select the appropriate track and the heads of all platters
are synchronized and move together as one.
Each track is broken up into sectors of data and the platters rotate to line up the sector
with the head to read the requested data.
Similar to main memory an important challenge in disk storage is dealing with failures.
In a 100 disk system for example if the mean time to failure or the expected lifetime of
each disk is five years then over a long period of time we're looking at one disk failing
every 18 days on average.
So we definitely need a way to recover data stored on failed disks.
RAID or redundant array of inexpensive disks is a class of standard schemes for redundant
storage.
Note that an important distinction to memory ECC is that with disk we have diagnostics
that can tell us when and which disks have failed.
So detection of failures is not necessarily a concern.
We just need to be able to recover the data in the failed disk in the mean time until
the disk is replaced.
The baseline disk storage system provides no failure protection.
This is generally referred to as RAID 0.
Here data is stored in coarse-grained blocks and striped across the disks in a round robin
fashion to allow for parallel access and faster effective bandwidth.
RAID 1 is the simplest form of failure recovery which replicates all data by using twice as
many disks.
This is known as mirroring.
So every right to a block is performed on both the primary disk and the redundant disk.
Then if the primary fails we simply switch to the redundant one.
RAID 3 takes a parity approach just like in ECC.
The idea is to use bitwise interleaving across disks and introduce an additional disk for
storing the parity bits.
With the disk failure we can recover the failed bits by exclusive oring the remaining bits.
RAID 4 extends this to block interleaved parity to allow for parallel accesses to non-contiguous
data sectors.
And RAID 5, which is the most commonly used today, distributes the parity blocks across
the disks to improve parallelism when performing writes, since every data write needs to update
the parity block as well, which ends up bottlenecking the parity disk in RAID 4.
So far our processors addresses have all represented storage in DRAM.
How are we going to update our processor to communicate with disk or any other IO device?
There are generally two mechanisms.
The first is memory mapped IO, which dedicates specific memory addresses to be IO registers
that control the IO device instead of mapping to physical DRAM.
The program can then send commands and receive information from the device by performing
loads and stores on that address.
So for example, to issue an IO command, we would encode our command into the data word
that we store into this memory address.
Note though that memory mapped loads and stores need to be declared uncashable and thus bypass
the cache, because these addresses aren't real memory storage, but actually control
signals on the IO device.
The second approach is to add special opcodes in the instruction set for performing IO commands.
These are dedicated instructions exclusively for reading and writing the IO device registers.
When these instructions are executed, corresponding IO commands are generated and sent over the
IO bus to the designated device.
Now that we can send commands to IO devices, we need a way for the IO device to communicate
back.
Again, there are two approaches.
The first is by polling or continuously reading the IO register of the corresponding IO device
until it gets updated.
Though very simple to implement, this usually wastes a lot of CPU cycles since for much
of the time, the processor is doing nothing but fetching instructions in a loop that's
just reading the IO register until some event occurs.
The second approach is to enable interrupts from IO devices.
These are functionally similar to our exceptions, except they occur asynchronously with the
processor.
As with exceptions, a cause register and handler routine provide the mechanism to the software
to respond accordingly to these IO interrupts.
Let's dig into different IO fabrics.
Those are a common, simple form of network used to connect devices in a computer system.
So far, our discussions have focused on the processor memory bus.
Unfortunately, these are not as straightforward as simply connecting all the IO devices onto
the same processor memory bus, as shown in the top, because this is usually infeasible
since the IO devices would incur overhead on the bandwidth between the memory and processor,
and there's no need for most IO devices, like a mouse, to have such high bandwidth to the
processor.
DRAM is relatively slow already.
We do not want it to get slower.
So as shown in the middle, modern systems will usually have a dedicated processor memory
bus, and then bus adapters would connect IO devices together via specialized IO buses.
In fact, most systems would take this further and use a backplane bus to move all the IO
devices off the main processor memory bus.
So what is a bus?
Basically, it's just a bunch of wires that's used to communicate information back and forth.
Typically it's shared to make routing wires easier, so we need a mechanism to arbitrate
and decide whose turn it is to send on the bus.
We need control signals, data signals, and address signals to uniquely identify specific
IO devices and control registers.
Buses generally come in two flavors.
Synchronous buses have a clock, so everyone connected to the bus watches the clock and
registers data and commands at the appropriate phases.
Bus transactions can take a fixed or variable number of cycles depending on the design.
Because of the built-in synchronization, bus transactions are usually much faster on synchronous
buses.
But conversely, the fact that an accurate clock needs to be maintained, the bus wires
can't be too long without incurring significant clock skew.
For these reasons, the processor memory bus is often synchronous.
Conversely, asynchronous buses require a lot of handshaking to coordinate all the information
transfer per transaction.
This is slower, but is a lot more flexible, which makes them well suited for lower bandwidth
IO buses.
This slide illustrates an example of a typical asynchronous handshaking protocol for a simple
transaction with a request and a data response.
So in the first step, the bus master sends a read request by asserting the read request
line and sending the request information on the main bus line.
Then in step two, the bus target receives the request and responds with an acknowledgement
signal.
This lets the master know that it can stop sending the request, and when it does so,
the target de-asserts its acknowledgement.
At this point, the master can wait for a response or send a new request to a different device.
When the original target is ready to provide the data response, perhaps after the disk
heads moved and it reads in a new sector, it indicates data ready in step five, and
just like before, the master now asserts the acknowledgement upon receiving the data,
and when the target sees this, they de-assert the data ready signal to complete the transaction.
One last thing about IO devices is how they interact with the caches.
Using direct memory access, or DMA, the CPU can allow IO devices to read and write from
main memory on their own.
But if we perform IO in front of the caches, as shown here, we end up slowing down the
CPU because now the IO devices are occupying part of the access bandwidth that the processor
needs to perform cached loads and stores.
So generally, for performance, IO devices will be pushed back closer to the memory bus.
But the challenge here now is that if an IO device needs to be read from memory, it may
not get the most up-to-date version of the data since the caches may not have written
back their modifications.
This is known as the cache coherence problem, which we'll discuss in more detail later
in the course.
So in order to support this, the caches generally have to be flushed before allowing IO to read
and write memory.
Let's end this lecture with an exercise that extends our discussion on sected hamming
codes.
This time, you go into memory and read the 8-bit code word.
You find that a bit flip has actually occurred, and the code word now looks like 00101001.
Your goal is to recover the original data word.
Please pause the video, calculate the syndromes, and figure out which bit has flipped.
Let's calculate the syndromes one bit at a time.
Syndrome bit one is the exclusive OR of every odd bit, which gives us one.
Then syndrome bit two is the exclusive OR of code word bits W2, W3, W6, and W7, which
is equal to one.
Then the same is done to compute syndrome bit three and the parity syndrome bit.
In this, we can now see that the syndrome is pointing to code word bit W3 is the culprit.
Thus code word bit W3 is the only bit that's wrong.
So to recover the original data word, we simply grab the code word bits that correspond to
data bits one through four and flip W3 back so we get the correct B1.
And there we have the original four bit data word, 0101.